Elisha Kent Kane Papers 1810-1973 1843-1857 Mss.B.K132
American Philosophical Society
From the beginning, Kane was concerned that news of his relationship with Fox could harm his reputation while he was away, so he enlisted the help of Cornelius Grinnell and younger brother Robert Patterson Kane to help safeguard Elisha's reputation. Patterson and Grinnell were to act as couriers for correspondence between Fox and Kane and they were instructed to quell any rumors that arose. Kane left his correspondence regarding his role in Maggie's education with his brother in order to leave a paper trail indicating that he was nothing more than a generous benefactor of the young woman.
There were other matters to worry about as well -- Kane's health, as usual, among them. In April 1853, just one month prior to sailing, Kane was stricken with rheumatic fever, but even after being confined to bed for three weeks, unsure whether he might die, he decided that he would make a go of the expedition. Such an unpromising beginning was a sign of things to come. The usual bouts of seasickness and an inexperienced crew added to the concerns, but it was only when the expedition reached the Arctic that the real troubles began.
Already concerned that he might be trumped in the discovery of the Open Polar Sea, Kane grew frantic upon receiving a letters from Lady Jane Franklin informing him that Capt. Edward Inglefield was setting out in one of England's best steam-powered ships to follow the rescue path that Kane had pursued in 1850-1851. Although Inglefield had only been sent to the Arctic to deliver supplies to five ships on Beechey Island, Lady Franklin's letter led Kane to adopt a more aggressive course than he had originally planned, crossing directly through Mellville Bay. Although this route stood to save time, it would expose the ship to treacherous icebergs which blocked the entrances to Smith and Lancaster Sounds, and Kane recognized that by taking this course he would also risk being frozen into an ice floe for the winter. He decided to take the chance.
Ominously, while crossing Mellville Bay, the Advance suffered a head-on collision with an iceberg that destroyed the jig-boom and one of the lifeboats, yet the ship still made remarkable time. By early August, with the entrance to Smith Sound in sight, the Advance stopped at Littleton Island to leave provisions and a lifeboat for future emergencies before pushing northward, and it was there that their troubles really began. Facing lashing storms and ice-clogged waters, Kane ultimately had to order his men to strap themselves into harnesses and pull the ship north. By late August, the Advance had traveled further north than any previous expedition (by the American route), but Kane demanded they push still further. But when the crew protested -- and more importantly, when it was ascertained that no further progress could be made due to heavy ice -- Kane agreed that they should stay put and wait for spring. While the American public waited and worried, Kane and his crew settled in for the winter.
The crew prepared for winter by building supply houses on shore, a wooden cover for the ship's deck, and a kennel for the dogs. Repeated attempts to rid themselves of the ship's rat population were somewhat successful but the methods caused a few anxious moments. The first attempt using noxious fumes nearly killed the cook, and the second, asphyxiation by carbon monoxide, set the deck on fire and caused Kane and another crewmember to lose consciousness while battling the blaze.
By mid-October, when the sun disappeared, all activity ground to a halt, and Kane and his crew were confined below deck to ride out a harsh winter ridden with scurvy and sensory deprivation, and more than a few flares of temper and fist fights. By February, with the sun barely visible, Kane wasted no time in returning to the mission, selecting eight members of the crew to attempt to reach Humboldt glacier and beyond. Ignoring the bitter cold and the protests of the experienced crew members that it was still too early to proceed, he sent his squad northward in mid-March.
The attempt was short-lived. Within a week of their departure, three of the men stumbled back to ship with news that the others were ill and freezing. Kane immediately led a party to rescue the men, an excursion that took fifty hours in temperatures that fell at times to fifty below zero. At the same time, the crew spied several Inuit hunters from Etah, a small village just 70 miles to the south, and invited them on board, where they sat down to a meal of raw walrus that the Inuit had brought with them. With the help of Carl Christian Peterson, a Danish crew member fluent in Inuktitut, Kane was able to communicate with the Inuit, enlisting their help for the upcoming winter.
As spring approached, Kane began to implement his plan to head north in search of the Open Polar Sea. First, he intended to send six of his men by foot to Humboldt Glacier, with him and another crewmember following on a sledge with provisions. They would then cross the channel to the American side and search for openings to the Open Polar Sea. As May -- and warmer weather -- approached, Kane realized that if he was to make a move, it would have to be before rising temperatures melted the ice. Yet once again, nothing went quite right. Heavy snowdrifts and the effects of scurvy and snowblindness stalled the expedition, and the crew discovered that all the food they had cached during the previous fall had been eaten by polar bears. Eventually, though, a small party from Kane's crew made it to Humboldt Glacier and crossed the still-frozen "Kane Basin." Despite battling snow blindness, they managed to travel over two hundred miles in all. Within a week of the first group's return to the ship, Kane sent out a second party of six men to travel beyond Humboldt Glacier to see if they could verify the existence of an opening to the Open Polar Sea.
On June 5, the men set off for Humboldt Glacier, two of whom continued northward after the others attempted to ascend the glacier and failed. Kane feared the worst for the two, but on July 3rd, they returned with the news that Kane had longed to hear: they had discovered the Open Polar Sea. They described how Kane Basin narrowed into a channel, and as they pressed further north, they noticed thinning ice and swarms of birds, including an open water species, the Arctic Petrel. They climbed a cape and from a 480 foot height, they saw nothing but open water. Kane was elated: having attained their goal, it looked as if he and his crew could finally focus on going home. There were only two small problems: the basin was frozen solid, completely blocking the way and the ship itself was completely iced in. It appeared that the Advance might face yet another Arctic winter.
Any hopes that the warm temperatures and strong winds might break up the floe were dashed when Kane discovered that new ice was already beginning to form and that the escape route was narrowing further. As August drew to a close, Kane accepted that the ship was trapped, but several members of the crew began to plan their escape. Feeling that he could not, in good conscience, force them to stay, Kane announced on August 23rd that if any men wished to strike out on their own, he would not stop them. Only five elected to stay: the others he made sign documents attesting that they were deserting and that Kane was no longer responsible for them. To his credit, Kane suppressed his anger long enough to bid the departing men good luck and to assure them that should they decide to return, they would be welcomed.
Kane and the remaining crew prepared for another Arctic winter, fortified with a year's experience and some valuable lessons in survival learned from the Inuit. Their first task was to insulate the ship to make it as "igloo-like" as possible. Although the darkness was oppressive, the relative comfort of the ship as well as the mutual hunting agreement with the people of Etah promised to make the winter months much more bearable. In early December, two deserters returned to the Advance and the others arrived shortly thereafter, having never made it to Upernavik. Kane suppressed his resentment and welcomed them as promised, even though sheltering the extra men proved to be a big challenge -- one of several as it turned out.
The cramped living space and strain on food stores increased tensions among the men, and illness, falling temperatures, and diminishing fuel supplies added to the misery. Tempers flared along with illness and insubordination. Kane kept discipline by calling offenders up on deck individually and bashing them "in the side of the head with a heavy metal belaying pin." This, it seemed, was an effective if temporary method.
The food shortage was the most critical issue, and Kane's hopes of leaning on the generosity of the Inuit were dashed when it was discovered that the residents of Etah were starving, too. Kane arranged to combine efforts with the Inuit in hunting, and together they managed to kill a walrus, saving both groups from starvation. Discipline, however, remained an issue. Two crewmembers, William Godfrey and John Blake, were discovered to be planning to steal a sledge bound for Etah. Although the men were caught in time and were beaten with a "leaden fist," Godfrey managed to escape on foot. Still weak from disease and hunger, the crew suffered for two weeks before the would-be thief returned with the sledge filled with meat. Godfrey refused to board the ship even when Kane brandished a rifle and shot at him, but instead ran off. Although Kane was furious, the meat helped restore the crew's health and spirits. Godfrey later claimed that he had not deserted a second time because he had never entered into an agreement with Kane upon his return from the first secession.
As spring approached, the crew's health and morale slowly improved and preparations began for the journey home. Although Kane was disappointed that he had been unable to see the Open Polar Sea for himself, he did manage to see Humboldt Glacier. On May 20, 1855, he and his crew began pulling their whale boats (their ship having been dismantled for fuel) over the ice to open water. By mid-June they were in Etah, and after waiting out a short spell of severe weather, they bid their Inuit friends farewell and set off for Upernavik.
In a punishing journey that left one crewmember dead, the small boats were pitched about violently in the ice-filled waters, and several times the men had to take cover from to heavy winds and ice. Solid ice at the base of Cape York led Kane to move out into Melville Bay instead of staying close to shore and waiting for the ice to move. By early August, however, Kane and his crew reached Upernavik, and from there they passed to Godhavn and on September 11th, met up with an American ship sent to their rescue.
When Kane arrived in New York on October 11th, 1854, he was once again accorded a hero's welcome. Advised by his family to handle his reception with humility and gratitude, he thanked the nation for their interest and concern, and much to his relief, no one on the crew sought to contradict his account of his crew's camaraderie and unity, or his own strong leadership. As it turned out, his greatest challenge lay within his own family: they were still very much opposed to his relationship with Maggie Fox.
Maggie had moved to Philadelphia in late September 1854 in anticipation of Kane's arrival, and two days later, the two were together at Clinton Place. The long-awaited reunion, however, was not the romantic encounter anticipated. Instead, Maggie found Kane to be distracted and agitated. Bowing to family pressure to cut off the relationship, he pleaded with Maggie to sign a note stating that their relationship was purely platonic. She refused. He returned a few days later with a reporter in tow, requesting that she affirm that they had never been engaged. Again, Maggie refused.
Rumors of Kane's engagement began to circulate widely, and even his departure for Washington, D.C., to give an official account of the expedition did nothing to quash them. To the family's dismay, a small newspaper in upstate New York reported the engagement, and soon major newspapers across the country were reprinting the story. Using its influence, the Kane family forced retraction of the story, but when Kane failed to refute the retraction, Maggie ended the relationship.
Nevertheless, he and Maggie continued to correspond. Kane clearly agonized over his decision but he and his family had built his public image very carefully and were not about to let a fling with a Spiritualist undo their hard work. Maggie, who had to preserve her own reputation, felt she had little choice either. Marriage, one possible solution, would preserve Maggie's reputation, but diminish the Kane family's standing -- something he was unwilling or unable to do until he was financially solvent. In the meantime, Maggie, her sister Kate, and their mother moved to 22nd Street in New York.
The Navy had already given Kane permission to publish his account of his Arctic experiences and had paid him for the time it took to write it. It was a generous arrangement, perhaps because the Navy had suffered criticism for not initially supporting Kane's expedition. At any rate, Kane wasted no time in picking a publisher, George W. Childs, who also worked aggressively to promote Kane's image -- so aggressively in fact, that his efforts to goad Congress into purchasing a large number of copies resulted in accusations that Kane was using his family's political connections for personal gain. Some of Child's other efforts fared better, including marketing the book at trade shows and selling it door-to-door, and Kane's public appearances also increased sales. Although the book was well-received and sold well, Kane was miserable. In addition to being unable to marry Maggie Fox, he had another problem: Lady Jane Franklin was determined that he head yet another expedition to rescue her husband.
Lady Franklin was, by all accounts, a determined advocate for her still-missing husband, and although nine years had elapsed since her husband had disappeared, she was effective at ratcheting up public pressure to save him. Kane felt obligated to lead the expedition and in August 1856, he began efforts to secure support. Kane spent the remainder of the fall (as he had the spring and summer) with Fox at her family's New York residence. By this point, her family had come to accept Kane as a sincere suitor, and he was welcome in their home, yet because his own family continued to hold back, he took great pains to conceal the relationship. Only his brother Patterson was kept informed, and perhaps only then because Kane assured him of his discretion.
On October 11, 1856, Kane left for Liverpool, arriving in poor health after a rough crossing. His spirits must have been relatively high, because he entertained thoughts of securing funding for not one, but two expeditions, and he wrote to his parents to ask them to seek support in the United States. It was not to be. On October 29, Kane collapsed and was sent to the suburbs of London to rest. From there he traveled to Cuba to take advantage of the better climate. Kane and his steward, William Morton, left for St. Thomas on November 17, but on the voyage between St. Thomas and Cuba, Kane suffered a stroke.
Kane's brother Thomas was waiting in Havana, and was joined in mid-January by his mother, and his brother John. After a brief rally, Elisha suffered a second, more severe stroke, and on February 16, he died at the age of 37.
Bache, A.D., (Alexander Dallas), 1806-1867; Baird, Spencer Fullerton, 1823-1887; Blockley Hospital (Philadelphia, Pa.); Brooks, Henry; Colt, Samuel, 1814-1862; Cracroft, Sophia, 1816-1892; Cushing, Caleb, 1800-1879; Force, Peter, 1790-1868; Fox, Margaret, 1833-1893; Franklin, Jane Griffin, Lady, 1792-1875; Franklin, John, Sir, 1786-1847; Greeley, Horace, 1811-1872; Grinnell, Cornelius; Grinnell, Henry, 1799-1874; Harris, Thomas; Henry, Joseph, 1797-1878; Kane, John K., (John Kintzing), 1795-1858; Kane, Jane Duval Leiper; Kane, Robert Patterson, 1827-1906; Kane, Thomas Leiper, 1822-1883; Kennedy, John Pendleton, 1795-1870; Weaver, William H.; Abolition, emancipation, freedom; Africa; Africa--Description and travel; Americans Abroad; Arctic Indians; Arctic regions--Discovery and exploration; Arctic regions-Pictorial works; Asia Minor--Description and travel; Bills.; China--Foreign relations--United States; Colonization, repatriation; Egypt--Description and travel; Engravings.; Exploration; Exploration.; Explorers--United States; Family Correspondence; General Correspondence; Geometry--Study and teaching; Grinnell Expedition, 1st, 1850-1851; Grinnell Expedition, 2d, 1853-1855; Hospitals--Pennsylvania; Indians of North America--Nunavut; International Travel; Inuit--Canada; Inuit--Greenland; Inuit--Nunavut--Baffin Island; Journals (notebooks); Lectures; Letterbooks; Liberia--Description and travel; Logbooks; Maps.; Marriage and Family Life; Medicine--Practice--Pennsylvania; Medicine--Study and teaching--Pennsylvania; Meteorology--Arctic Regions; Mexico--Description and travel; Mineralogy--Study and teaching; North Carolina--Description and travel; Northwest Passage; Notebooks; Obstetrics; Philadelphia (Pa.)--Hospitals; Philadelphia. General Hospital; Plantations; Receipts; Silhouettes; Sketches.; Slave trade--Africa; Slaves, slavery, slave trade; Social Life and Custom; Travel Narratives and Journals; United States--Foreign relations--China; United States. Navy; Watercolors
- Series I. Correspondence, 1810-1953 (bulk: 1843-1857); 5.5 linear feet
  Scope and Contents note
  Personal and public correspondence of Elisha Kent Kane, dating primarily from his college days in the early 1840s through his death in 1857. Touching on all aspects of Kane's personal life (including his scandalous affairs) and his numerous expeditions around the world, the correspondence forms an important resource for examining the public and private construction of one of America's foremost mid-Victorian explorers.
  - 1845, 7 items; Abbott, Henry (Box 1)
  - 1852-1853, 3 items; Abbott, W. M. (Box 1)
  - 1851-1853, 2 items; Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia. (Box 1)
  - 1852, 2 items; Addison, S. R. (Box 1)
  - 1839-1842, 9 items; Admission cards (Box 1)
  - 1850-1851, 16 folders; Logbook (Box 1)
    - Folder 1, May -June 1850 (Box 1)
    - Folder 2, July 1850 (Box 1)
    - Folder 3, August 1850 (Box 1)
    - Folder 4, September 1850 (Box 1)
    - Folder 5, October 1850 (Box 1)
    - Folder 6, November 1850 (Box 1)
    - Folder 7, December 1850 (Box 1)
    - Folder 8, January 1851 (Box 1)
    - Folder 9, February 1851 (Box 1)
    - Folder 10, March 1851 (Box 1)
    - Folder 11, April 1851 (Box 1)
    - Folder 12, May 1851 (Box 1)
    - Folder 13, June 1851 (Box 1)
    - Folder 14, July 1851 (Box 1)
    - Folder 15, August 1851 (Box 1)
    - Folder 16, September 1851 (Box 1)
  - 1852 May 8, 1 item; Agassiz, Louis, 1807-1873 (Box 1)
  - 1852 December 19, 1 item; Ahrens, C. (Box 1)
  - 1852 February 17, 1 item; Allderice, John A. (Box 1)
  - 1856 October 8, 1 item; Allibone, F. Austin (Box 1)
  - 1847 September 11, 1 item; Appleton, John (Box 1)
  - n.d., 1 item; Arills (?), Thomas (Box 1)
  - 1852 June 12, 1 item; Audubon, Vincent G. (Box 1)
  - 1850 September 13, 1 item; Austen, Capt. (Box 1)
  - 1853 March 9, n.d., 2 items; Ayres, W. O. (Box 1)
  - 1845-1852, 10 items; Bache, A.D., (Alexander Dallas), 1806-1867 (Box 1)
  - 1847-1849, 3 items; Bache, Benjamin Franklin, 1769-1798 (Box 1)
  - n.d., 2 items; Bailey and Co. (Box 1)
  - 1852-1853, 6 items; Baird, Spencer Fullerton, 1823-1887 (Box 1)
  - 1846 May 12, 2 items; Bancroft, George, 1800-1891 (Box 1)
  - 1853, 2 items; Barclay, Arthur (Box 1)
  - 1810 November 20, 1 item; Baring Bros. (Box 1)
  - 1855-1856, 2 items; Barnes, John (Box 1)
  - 1844, 2 items; Baron, D., Jr. (Box 1)
  - 1847 November 8, 1 item; Barr, James T. (Box 1)
  - 1853 March 5, 1 item; Barritt, G. W. (Box 1)
  - 1853 March 11, 1 item; Barrow, John (Box 1)
  - 1857 March 5, n.d., 2 items; Beaufort, F. (Box 1)
  - 1850 April 29, 1 item; Beck, Morris B. (Box 1)
  - 1852, 1 item; Bell, William (Box 1)
  - 1852-1853, 3 items; Bellot, J. (Box 1)
  - 1856 October 31, 1 item; Better, T. N. (Box 1)
  - 1849-n.d., 3 items; Bier, G. H. (Box 1)
  - n.d., 1 item; Bigelow, Mr. (Box 1)
  - n.d., 1 item; Billard, Dr. (Box 1)
  - n.d., 21 items; Biographical notes (Box 1)
  - 1852 December 13, 1 item; Blair, T. and W. (Box 1)
  - 1853 February 9, 1 item; Blanchard, George S. (Box 1)
  - 1852-1853, 4 items; Bloodgood, S. DeWitt (Box 1)
  - 1856 January 14, 1 item; Boker, George H., (George Henry), 1823-1890 (Box 1)
  - 1853, 2 items; Borden, Gail, Jr. (Box 1)
  - 1853, 2 items; Borland, Solon (Box 1)
  - 1852 March 1, 1 item; Bouring, J. C. (Box 1)
  - 1856 April 11, 1 item; Bradley, Ravenel (Box 1)
  - 1853 January 23, 1 item; Breand, Samuel (Box 1)
  - 1853 February 18, 1 item; Brewer, Thomas Mayo (Box 1)
  - 1852 October 21, 1 item; Briggs, G. W. (Box 1)
  - 1852 October 18, 1 item; Brigham, C. H. (Box 1)
  - 1852-1853, 7 items; Brooks, Henry (Box 1)
  - 1850, 2 items; Brown, Isaac N. (Box 1)
  - 1852-1853, 2 items; Browne, Peter A (Box 1)
  - n.d., 1 item; Brownlee, Mr. (Box 1)
  - 1852 December 29, 1 item; Butler, G. B. (Box 1)
  - 1853 March 31, 1 item; Butler, Pierce (Box 1)
  - 1849 November 4, 1 item; Cadwalader, John (Box 2)
  - 1845 July 17, 1 item; Camba, Andres G. (Box 2)
  - 1852 September 27, 1 item; Carpenter, W. F. (Box 2)
  - 1843 April 12, 1 item; Carson, Joseph (Box 2)
  - n.d., 1 item; Carter, R. R. (Box 2)
  - 1852 December 24, 1 item; Caruthers, Horace (Box 2)
  - n.d., 1 item; Cathrall, Charles E. (Box 2)
  - 1843 February 20, 1 item; Chapman, Nathaniel (Box 2)
  - 1856 October 4, 1 item; Childs, George W. (Box 2)
  - 1848 July 28, 1 item; Childs, Thomas (Box 2)
  - 1846-1852, 2 items; Clarke, R. R. (Box 2)
  - n.d., 26 items; Clippings from Illustrated London News (Box 2)
  - 1852 November 23, 1 item; Clymer, William B. (Box 2)
  - 1852, 2 items; Colson, C. W. (Box 2)
  - 1852-1853, 3 item; Colt, Samuel, 1814-1862 (Box 2)
  - 1853 March 3, 1 item; Corbit, William T. (Box 2)
  - 1953, 2 items; Corner, George Washington, 1889-1981 (Box 2)
  - 1851 January 21, 1 item; Coure, R. (Box 2)
  - 1852-1857, 15 items; Cracoft, Sophia (Box 2)
  - 1855 December 8, 1 item; Crampton, John F. (Box 2)
  - 1856 January 18, 1 item; Cresson, E. G. (Box 2)
  - Cuba: translations of letters regarding treatment of Men of Color, 1841; 9p. (Box 2)
  - 1920 March 30, 1 item; Cudworth, Warren H. (Box 2)
  - n.d., 1 item; Cummings, A. (Box 2)
  - 1852 February 4, 1 item; Cummings, E. (Box 2)
  - 1856 October 5, 1 item; Curtis, G. W. (Box 2)
  - 1853 May 7, 1 item; Cushing, Caleb, 1800-1879 (Box 2)
  - 1847-1848, 2 item; Dallas, G. M. (Box 2)
  - 1848 April 1, 1 item; Davidson, Lionel (Box 2)
  - 1858 February 12, 1 item; Davis, W. W. H. (Box 2)
  - n.d., 1 item; Dawson, John L. (Box 2)
  - 1847-1851, 7 items; Dayton, A. O. (Box 2)
  - 1850-1852, 17 items; DeHaven, E. J. (Box 2)
  - 1858 February 10, 1 item; De la Mano, William (Box 2)
  - n.d., 1 item; Delano, J. C. (Box 2)
  - 1843 April 18, 1 item; Delaware Co. Insurance Company (Box 2)
  - 1848 May 18, 1 item; Denistown, Wood and Co. (Box 2)
  - n.d., 1 item; Dent, Mr. (Box 2)
  - 1936 September 22, 1 item; Dewees, William P. (Box 2)
  - 1856 October 6, 1 item; DeWitt, Thomas (Box 2)
  - 1848, 2 items; Dickerson, Mahlon (Box 2)
  - 1847, 4 items; Dillard, J. (Box 2)
  - 1853, 3 items; Dobbin, J. C. (Box 2)
  - 1847 November 5, 1 item; Douglas, S. N. (Box 2)
  - 1848 March 19, 1 item; Dulany, William (Box 2)
  - 1856-n.d., 3 items; Dunglison, Robley, 1798-1869 (Box 2)